so we'll do a majima 15 today um in
terms of our little suta
study um and
um that suta it's called anuman sua or
evaluation how it's
translated and um so it's about when V
mogana was staying near
the near the land of buers at crocodile Hill
near the land of buers at crocodile Hill
in the Deer
Park so he was talking to the to the
buikus about the nature of
admonishment and how some B might be
hard to admonish and having qualities
that that keep him that
way um so then he explained on the on
those qualities and then obviously
continued in talking of how to abandon
them and uh so the Su goes suppose a
biku invites other BOS to admonish him
but he's hard to admonish having
qualities that make him hard to admonish
he's not forbearing does not take
instructions respectfully so his
spiritual companions don't think it's
worth advising or instructing him and
they don't regard him as
trustworthy what are the qualities that
make him hard to admonish firstly a biku
has evil wishes having fallen under the
sway of evil wishes this is the quality
that makes him difficult to admonish so
evil wish then B who glorifies himself
puts others down or he's prone to anger
overcome by anger he's prone to anger
resentful due to anger he is stubborn
due to anger blurts out words bordering
on anger he objects the accuser when
he's accused when accused he rebukes the
accuser when accused he retorts to the
accuser when accused he Dodges the issue
distracts the discussion with irrelevant
points gets flustered and displays hate
and bitterness when accused he's unable
to account for the evidence
um he denigrates and he's contentious
he's jealous and stingy devious
deceitful stubborn and
arrogant that all obviously results in
then that furthermore that b is attached
to his own views holding them tight
refusing to let go that too is the
quality that makes him difficult to
admonish the reason why I wanted to do
this suta is basically you could simply
replace all the all the when the Buddha
when the m talks about admonishment just
replace the word admonish with um
disagreed with so suppose aiku basically
encounters or well if we replace
admonish with disagree with then you
realize that this whole Su can apply to
anyone it's not just for the beus and in
terms of their V admonishment and
similar it's
basically whenever somebody disagrees
with you do you have the qualities that make
you do you have the qualities that make
it hard for you to to stay rational to
to to not lose perspective so suppose a
b invites other BOS to disagree with him
to find the points of disagreement he's
hard to disagree with having qualities
that make him so and um so from that
point of view you can then include
yourself in this simply well in this
practice and simply start um
re-evaluating your own mindsets when you
experience this agreement in the world
take yourself for example and just see
like whether uh when you experience
disagreement when somebody disagrees
with you on the level of your views on
the level of how things should be done
uh and
similar do you uh find that experience
in and of itself
uncomfortable are you resisting it if so
you then partake in the qualities that
are making you hard to admonish so the
point here is is that it's not even that
you necessarily need to be in the
wrong like like these B like in this
instance they might be they might be uh
uh mistakenly admonishing this ble they
might be actually they might be the ones
who factually wrong but the point is
it's not about that it's about whether
you from your individual point of view
when experiencing the experience of
admonishment or
disagreement uh are you affected by that
regardless of whether that admonishment
is right or wrong so are you uh
resisting that experience are you not
forbearing do you not take what was said
uh respectfully in other words are you
losing perspective and giving into
anger uh and that's exactly what what
the Su then goes on to describe so see
like what are the qualities that make
you hard to disagree
with so evil wishes in other words do
you have desires that are rooted in
greed aversion distraction if you're
still partaking in those desires to to
to to the extent you're partaking in
them you will be under that sway of evil
wishes so it's not like the most coarse
UNH wholesome evil horrible wishes no
anything rooted in GRE division delusion
it's it's partaking in in Mara it's
partaking in evil so to speak so for as
long as you do have such wishes that
that's already one quality they will
make you resist the experience of
admonishment they will make you have ill
will towards it um they will make you
basically difficult to disagree with the
the second then example is biku
glorifies himself and puts others down
again you could take this in this
obviously like a very like a caricature
manner like some absolutely fully full
of himself ConEd person but the same
principle remains even on the on the on
the subtler levels such as again do you
just value your views and opinions
because they're
yours simply for that reason you put
them first and because if there is a
form of disagreement encountered your
first response is to put the other
person down not to hear what they have
to say and that's exactly what leads to
next he's prone to anger overcome by
anger so you you just review your mind
like you can think this doesn't apply to
me for example you can say oh no this
doesn't apply to me I I'm I'm I don't
have evil wishes uh but then okay well
do have any wishes rooted in sensuality
if the answer is yes then you do have
evil wishes then you can say well I
don't get angry I'm not prone to anger
okay sure overall you're probably not
you might not be an angry person but
when you experience disagreement are you
irritated when somebody says the
displeasing words to you whether they're
right or wrong is irrelevant we're
simply talking about being subjected to
that type of experience and if so then
are you prone to irritation are you
resentful due to anger are you stubborn
in other words do you then just double
down in your points regardless of what's
presented as a counter argument and so
on do you blurt out words so it's like
you can review all these things and see
has it happened how often has it
happened and so on if so means you still
partake in that
domain and um then it goes further so
it's like when accused so when disagreed
with do you object the person that
disagreed with you do you rebuke the
person that accuse you do you retort to
them in other words do you look past the
fact that there is a point they're
making against you and attacking them at
hominy instead so when accused he
doesn't look at the accusation and
present the counter argument and so on
no he objects the person that accused
him when rebuked he he when when accused
he rebukes how dare you accuse me or who
do you think you are and so on um or he
retorts to the accuser either way he
does not address the
accusation and see that's the point like
even if the accusation is wrong you are
in wrong as well if you are uh looking
if you if you don't have perspective in
regard to it and you won't have
perspective in regard to it if you're
resisting the discomfort of it and you
would be resisting the discomfort of it
if you are still under the evil wishes
if you still give in to anger if you
have not purified your virtue and tamed
your mind uh on account of it so all
these ad hominum attacks
would be pretty much self-defense
mechanisms that might not even be
necessary because you still might be in
the right like the accusation might be
wrong you might be right but the fact is
that you have a face of the accuser as
the most important the image of the
accuser is associated for you with the
accusation so that's why even your uh
response to that is irrational it's not
on the level of of the of the context
that matters and it's passing the point
of addressing the accusation and going
after the accuser and that in end of
itself makes you wrong obviously like
both parties can be partaking in the
same this is this applies to to anyone
really the one that's accusing or the
accuser the one that's disagreeing with
or the disagreed with like if you are
honest you need to re-evaluate your own
mind and simply as I said not look for
the instances when you were accused and
how you act just overall do I have
wishes of sense of sense desires
do I act out of irritation in regard to
this and that do I get ill will do I get
upset do do I give into anger is my
behavior purified are my senses tamed if
not you are partaking in this even if
you would have learned the perfect way
of psychotherapeutical management of
your expression and and and always
speaking softly and everything else you
still doing that out of ill will you're
doing that out of resent out of
stubbornness you're doing that aimed at
the accuser in other words you cannot
have the right perspective no matter how
hard you try because all these things
are covering it up and distorting it so
if if then that person is not go the Su
goes on says if accused he Dodges the
issue distracts the discussion with
irrelevant points gets flustered
displays hate or bitterness again just
you you can you can simply look at it
it's like okay even if you're not
engaging with the um ad hominum attacks
you ask yourself are you first and
foremost do you immediately go on a
defensive mode when there is a
disagreement presented at you that's
already irrational like you have no
reason to go on a defensive you have no
reason to to immediately feel the
pressure of Defense you will feel it for
as long as you're not free from desires
for as long as you're not free from from
from ill will to a greater degree
because it's the discomfort of that
experience that you resist which then
projected either on the accuser or
avoiding the issue or either way you're
going to be wriggling um wiggling left
left and right basically trying to avoid
to address it because that would kind of
make it basically well make you feel the
full weight of it but the the catch
there is that the more you resist it the
more unpleasant it is so if you were to
stop resisting by default the
disagreements the the admonishment being
told off or being pointed as wrong or
maybe questioned even uh the the less
frightening it will be to face that but
as I said you can't just decide to start
doing that rightly despite of
psychotherapy tries to teacher you and
so on and and modern skillful
communication management you can only
start doing it rightly by removing the
the the unsuitable
qualities that the suit describes which
is the qualities of evil wishes if
wishes rooted in in in UNH wholesome
things do you are you is your mind still
gri with the desire with lust with ill
will with with um malice and and and so
on then it's like Oh by addressing those
things that's how you then get to face
the criticism or face the admonishment
and not automatically you know tighten
up and need to need to rort need to find
the way out need to uh question the
accuser rebuke him retort or distract
just as throwing million of other points
that you will not not you will not
address the original Point made against
you for as long as all these other
points that you now brought up on top of
it are not addressed as well first CU
it's important it's just basically you
know like a lawyer just throwing out
technicalities of the law to M the fact
that he knows his client wrong and he
just tries to drag it on until
everything gets bogged down in in in
details taken out of context and that's
how he sets him free so people do that
when again so they might not be
attacking somebody personally but they
still refuse to to acknowledge
uh the admonishment to acknowledge the
disagreement to see it for what it is
and then present their counter argument
because if you were truly and the reason
why people don't want to do that is
because they're not used to clarifying
their own
thinking with that with that as I said
with that rational reflection of okay my
view is
such I hold that this is right and
that's wrong why so start questioning
yourself already so by the time you
encounter disagreement in the world and
other people questioning you you would
have already done done that so many
times and your views would have been
fortified not through like skilled
avoidance and so on no they would have
been freed from contradictions because
if you start questioning yourself
rightly you will not have a problem in
uh in abandoning your views if you
discover discrepancies um in it if you if you
discrepancies um in it if you if you
find that it's contradictory if you find
that it's
incomplete you you won't be uh as
shocked to find that out if somebody
else points it out because you would
have done that beforehand already and
that's already the practice of reviewing
your behavior like are you acting out of
behavior like are you acting out of
anger are you acting out of will will
not just to kind of wallow in that yes
I'm a bad person something no no just so
that next time when these things present
when these choices of acting out of evil
wishes or desires or um anger or
arrogance when those choices are
presented I can actually see them as
opposed to only in hindsight discovered
that oh yeah I chose that and did that
and said that uh and that takes like
persist reflection you need to reflect
and invest effort into like dig this
thing up so to recognize them so to then
be able to not choose them when the
pressure is put on you so if a person
has already done that privately when
they encounter admonishment
disagreement right or wrong doesn't
matter they will have no problem in
seeing it for what it is and if it's
correct it's like oh yeah thank you for
pointing that out I I didn't think about
that if it's wrong again they won't
gloat or feel Superior accountable they
just say no you're mistaken because of
this this and this so your argument
doesn't add up not
mine and that's that's exactly what he
carries on the Su it says so
um he's attached to his own views um
he's oh sorry before that yes so so he
Dodges the issue he's unable to account
for the
evidence then he denigrates he's
contentious he's jealous stingy devious
deceitful stubborn and arrogant and then
because he's attached to his own views
holding them tight and refusing to let
go so these are the qualities that make
him hard to admonish in other words
these are the qualities that it will
make him unable to accept any form of to
accept the experience of this agreement
without being affected by it let's put
it that way so whether disagreement or
admonishment is right or wrong doesn't
matter he will first and foremost be
affected by it emotionally mentally even
if he has a perfect management of coping
never says the wrong thing internally
first and foremost he will be affected
by it and that's a problem for somebody
who wants to practice somebody wants to
count their mind and become
accomplishing dhama any any form of
being affected by experience is work to
do is something that needs to be
abandoned so then the Buddha goes uh Mak
goes and talks about the what are the
qualities that make him easy to admonish
and then he the opposite so he doesn't
he doesn't have evil wishes he's not
attached to his own views and so on um
so in such case a bik should evaluate
himself oh this person has evil wishes
he's fallen under the the sway of these
wishes uh and I should not like I I do
not like or approve of that person and
if I were to swall to to to fall under
the sway of evil wishes others wouldn't
like and approve of me in other words an
impartial Observer can always see in in an
Observer can always see in in an
argument like who is the irrational
one even if not necessarily wrong if
somebody's truly impartial they can see
oh this person is affected by this
they're not making sense they're they're
attack they're going add homonym
attacking or whatever so then the suda
carries on that a b should evaluate
himself in this way in regard to the
evil wishes anger malice
arrogance is he resorting to ad homm
attacks is he dodging the issue and so
on so then it says that the Su carries
on saying that suppose upon reflection B
recognizes these things in him these UNH
wholesome qualities that need to be
abandoned and he should make an effort
to give them
up so see that's another important Point
here it's not like you know then he
should practice this technique and do
that or counter it with this experience
and focus on that no he needs to
evaluate his mind his experience his
past actions past choices recent or
doesn't matter how how recent or not he
needs to detect determine that there are
still these unfavorable qualities in him
or that he's prone to them or that he
could engage with them and then abandon
that again abandon that through
recognition um recognize if there is not
enough uh negative
value attached to these UNH wholesome
qualities through reflection through
repeated reflection
when those qualities present themselves
you'll still act out of them you'll
still choose them but if you before they
present thems you reflect frequently and
you are putting a negative value on
those on those
qualities uh when they present
themselves that value will be your
mindfulness that negative value will be
your container from preventing you to
automatically just blur things out or
act or choose this or that that's un
wholesome um again that's why like the
would talked about like sense of Shame
and fear of wrongdoing are the guardians
of the world so these are like sense of
Shame is basically a negative value
attached to certain types of behavior
that result in shame so having sense of
Shame means that value protects you from
going down the path of those behaviors
ignoring the sense of Shame means going
down that that the paths of those
Behavior so you don't actually uh need
to like um be constantly sort of
dwelling in a sense of Shame you just
need to have that on the level of the
value that these things are bad I
understood that I reflected frequently
upon it so now that negative value is
attached to them so when I'm mindless
distracted and suddenly desires present
himself or real will it will come with
that negative value that I've been
cultivating in regard to it and that's
how sens straint starts bearing fruit
you can be you can be mindlessly
restrained and keep all the precepts and
and some and and uh not give into
anything but not allow
that um the weight of those choices to
come down to like on that level of
intention so you need to recognize that
the precepts and saying no to certain
things and so on needs to be uh
accompanied with a whole like a frequent
reflection on the level of values
whereby I'm not just not doing this or
that thing because some authori said so
I'm doing it because it's wrong and it's
from my harm how they s to say it but I
don't see I don't see that harm I don't
see why it's wrong exactly so now you
need to do the work and while still not
doing it you need to reflect and dig
deeper and recollect and bring back the
harm and discern it layer by layer by
layer and then you know a year or so
later or longer depending on how
diligent you were you wouldn't have to
think about it when the desire to do
such and such things presents itself
comes with implication of
harm so it might feel like you need to
fabricate the harm initially and and
it's true for some people but that's
because it will work because there is
effectual harm in those things that's
obscured so if sensuality were truly not
harmful no amount of you fabricating
harm and values of harm in regard to it
would make it be would make it imply
harm when it present itself but it is
actually harmful that's the part that's
not seen so then if you dwell and
frequently reflect upon that it will
become part of sensuality that hm that's
now seen that's how what the suas mean
when they say the danger becomes
apparent the danger that was always
implicit wasn't apparent before now
through withdrawal frequent reflection
upon it trying to discern it trying to
see more of it when it's there oh now
it's apparent now it's effortless to see
it so that's how the monke says because
when the Su say oh he just abandons
these qualities you think so so what how
I mean why did why didn't the Buddha say
more how do you abandon those qualities
do you do this or do you do that do you
practice concentration do you practice
that I don't know no it's just he
recognizes them he detects them for what
they are he sees harm in
them he attaches that negative value to
them through his own effort through his
own frequent recollection reflection and
so on so then when those things come up
again on their own they come with that
so it becomes effortless to say no to
them eventually not without a proper
amount of work so so that how you simply
abandon them you realize the work is on
the level of reshaping the value of well
reshaping the value of acting out of
sensuality ill will distraction if you
would have internally reshaped long
enough properly thoroughly through prior
sense restraint and guarding of the
sense doors and Taming of the mind it
results in everything that follows it
results in in Taming of the senses it
results in calmness it results in J it
results in Liberation so there's no
other work that's what in the others m
in the other Maj the similar of The
Chariot that we did says purification of
behavior leads to purification of the
mind that leads to purification of the
views that then leads to Joy and
Liberation and so on so it's there's
nothing else there it's not like that
the Buddha omitted some crucial parts of
the practice that only in contemporary
Buddhism and commentaries we find all
these techniques and so on and it's like
it doesn't exist because there is no
room for it
it's unnecessary like if you address the
root problem which is you willingly
choosing these unskillful qualities that
then make you irrational make you resist
um any discomfort of disagreement
discrepancy and so on if you willingly
stop choosing that um your views will be
purified you will not be you will not be
obstinately acting out of those things
and you will not continue to be affected
by the disagreements or discrepancy cuz
see like self-evaluating is already your
own attitude of looking for disagreement
with yourself so that's already the practice
yourself so that's already the practice
reviewing your behavior is there
anything that shouldn't be there from
obviously the value the standpoint of
somebody who wants to practice ad
dhama and uh so disagreement is good
discernment discrimination is
good done on that right level you
discriminate against good behavior and
bad behavior and that's exactly how you
bring yourself in line and uh and uh if
you're not doing it on that personal
level that's why it's so uncomfortable
when you encounter it coming at you
externally as I said even if it's
completely wrong like somebody can have
some ridiculous argument whatever against
ridiculous argument whatever against
your view and you will still be affected
by it first and foremost on that
personal level from a person who did
that although you know you even have the
the the the the correct so to speak um
argument against it they would show that
no they are the rational one they're the
contradictor their argument is
contradictory your isn't but the fact is
that on a personal level you're affected
by the experience of it to that extent
that is your wrongdoing you that should
not be happening either so that's of
course it's not going to be overnight
you know like these these layers of
irrationality and emotional response to
the discomfort it's not going to be
solved just just in a magical f snap but
you need to recognize that for as long
as there is a degree of that mental
resistance toward such experience of
admonishment being rebuked being
disagreed with being pointed out things
that that you don't necessarily want to
hear and so on it's like there is
absolutely no reason to be any any
resistance towards it um and if there is
no resistance towards it then as I said
you you will have no problem in because
you would you would not lose perspective
so you would immediately see through
whatever is presented at you it's like
oh yeah I did not consider
that thank you so you're easy to
admonish and then other people would be
willing and see like say if somebody who
also practice D who's actually maybe
developed even more than you are in
taming the mind and so on points things
at you from their better standpoint from
their greater development of their mind
and you are not uh irrationally
resisting it they'll do it again and
that's for your benefit factually that's
what this Sut specifically talks about
but as I said you can apply that in much
broader sense and even if they're not
speaking for your welfare they're just
criticizing you mindlessly you can use
that to see oh but am I affected by that
first and foremost regardless of like
how ridiculous their argument might be
and so on or whether you right or wrong
is just is this experience in and of
itself affecting me like do I feel like
a little at least twitch towards I want
to put them down or I want this or I
want that it's like do I remain unmoved
and and that's that's again oh I'm moved
there you go reevaluate that and then
see because there won't be any other
qualities because of which you're moved
it's what the Su lists which means if
I'm moved it has to be only because I
still choose a degree of
sensuality I still choose ill will
annoyance blurting out things I still
don't restrain my speech well enough
there you go develop one develop
two uh and there will be no more
movement even when such experience it
comes your way and again if there is no
more movement there is no there is no
shift there is no obscuring of the
perspective that you have so then you
would immediately see whether that
person CU sometimes somebody might even
criticize you while they actually agree
with you but they didn't quite
understand what you were saying so
they're kind of saying the same because
they misunderstood you but again if you
were affected by it you're going to
start arguing back without even actually
hold on but they are saying the same
just in different words and then you
would get to recognize that and clarify
the thing and it would be for the
benefit of them um so all of that it's
like see sometimes a person might want
to try okay so I'll start practicing all
these things I'll start practicing not
disagreeing and not doing this and not
being affected by it and um not going at
honm attacks and I will only listen to
the reason and I'll present this and you
can be partially successful but all of
that is the symptom of the issue the
issue being you still act out of desire
you still acting out of ill will you're
still acting out of distraction and
everything else that comes out of it so
you want to address it really as the
suta says you're evaluate mind for those
unskillful qualities are they still
there if you recognize them dwell day
and night on attaching UNH wholesome bad
value to them so when they come up
you'll immediately see them and you will
not be uh perpetually choosing the
course of action that's rooted in them